Guide to the Gustaf E. Lindskog Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Gustaf E. Lindskog Papers
1929-1987
Ms Coll 34
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
Thoracic surgeon Gustaf Lindskog was a member of the Department of Surgery from 1933 until his retirement in 1971. He chaired the department from 1948 to 1966. The collection consists primarily of his reports as head of the Thoracic Surgery Service of New Haven Hospital, talks including history of surgery lectures given at Yale, medical illustrations, and reprints. The restricted boxes contain Lindskog's notes on his surgical operations on named patients.
Lindskog, Gustaf Elmer, 1903-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carl Lindskog, 2011. Additional materials belonging to Lindskog, especially his history of surgery lectures, were donated earlier and added to the collection in 2015.
Custodial History
These materials were owned by Gustaf E. Lindskog.
Conditions Governing Access
Part of this collection is open for research.
Descriptions of operations and correspondence with or about named patients are restricted.
Biographical / Historical
Gustaf E. Lindskog, thoracic surgeon at Yale, was born in Boston in 1903. He graduated from the Massachusettts Agricultural College (now University of Massachusetts) in 1923, and received his M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1928. He interned at Lakeside Hospital in Cleveland. From 1929 to 1932, he was a resident in surgery at Yale. The following year he was a National Research Council Fellow at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston. In 1933, he returned to Yale as instructor of surgery and rose through the ranks to become the William Carmalt Professor of Surgery in 1948. Lindskog chaired the department from 1948 to 1966. In 1971 he retired but remained active in the Yale community. During World War II, he served for four years as a commander in the Navy Medical Corps and was stationed part of the time at the Philadelphia Naval Yard. In 1943, he worked with Louis S. Goodman and Alfred Gilman on the development of chemotherapy at Yale. They used nitrogen mustard in the treatment of a patient with lymphosarcoma. Lindskog was widely recognized for his contributions to thoracic surgery. He pioneered in the surgical resection of chronic pulmonary abscess. In addition to his many research articles, he was co-author with Averill Liebow and William Glenn on three editions of a major textbook of thoracic surgery, Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery with Related Pathology (1953, 1962, 1975). He died at the age of 99 in 2002.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains reports of the Thoracic Service at Yale, 1938-1946; statistics of various other surgical operations at Yale; lists of surgical residents; typescripts of lectures before various groups; medical illustrations by Armin Hemberger and others, and photographic illustrations from some of his papers; manuscripts of possibly unpublished papers; other miscellany; and reprints of Lindskog's articles. The restricted boxes contain Lindskog's descriptions of his surgical operations on named patients.
Arrangement
Organized in seven series: 1. Yale University School of Medicine Department of Surgery. 2. Lectures before various groups. 3. Medical drawings and photographs for some of Lindskog's publications. 4. Miscellany. 5. Reprints of Lindskog's papers. 6. Notes on surgical operations (restricted). 7. Lindskog's history of surgery lectures at Yale.
Chest -- Surgery; Diaphragmatic hernia; Lungs -- Cancer; Medicine -- History; Operations, Surgical; Residents (Medicine); Surgery -- History; Tuberculosis -- Surgery; Correspondence; Drawings (visual works); Medical records; Photographs; Surgeons -- Connecticut; Thoracic surgeons -- Connecticut; Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1886-1953; Hemberger, Armin B., 1896-1974; Lindskog, Gustaf Elmer, 1903-2002; Grace-New Haven Community Hospital; Harvard Medical School; New Haven Hospital (New Haven, Conn.); Lakeside Hospital (Cleveland, Ohio); Yale-New Haven Hospital; Yale University. Department of Surgery; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Yale University School of Medicine Department of Surgery, 1938-1968; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Note: Series 6 (restricted) is related to Series 1.
  - Reports of the Thoracic Service, Department of Surgery, New Haven Hospital, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Statistics of Hernia-Laparotomy Group, Extra-Abdominal Group, and "Minor operations", 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lists of Residents and Senior Assistant Residents in Surgery, 1948-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Also list of members of the "YNHH Society."
- Lectures before various groups, 1946-1987; Series II
  Titles transcribed from Lindskog's original folders. See Box 5 for history of medicine lectures at Yale.
  - "Bronchiogenic Carcinoma," presented at the American Surgical Association, 1946 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Surgical Lesions of the Diaphragm," presented to the Utah Medical Society ("unpublished"), 1948 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Problems and Results of the Surgery of Bronchiectasis," presented at the New England Surgical Society ("unpublished"), 1948 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Collateral Respiration and Collateral Circulation in the Normal and Diseased Lung," presented at the Mayo Foundation, 1949 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Collateral Respiration and Collateral Circulation in the Normal and Diseased Lung," presented at the Veterans Administration Hospital, Albuquerque, New Mexico, 1950 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Tenth Anniversary Remarks at Resident's Party", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Notes changes since Samuel C. Harvey retired ten years ago.
  - "A Survey of Acute and Chronic Empyema Thoracis - Diagnosis and Treatment," presented at Medical Department Grand Rounds ("unpublished"), circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Atelectasis: Its Causes and Treatment," American College of Surgeons, Atlantic City, Panel on Nontuberculous Infections of the Lungs and Pleura, 1962 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Foreign bodies," Clinical Lecture, Waterbury Hospital, 1972 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Medical drawings and photographs for some of Lindskog's publications, Series III
  Illustrations and photographs are of anatomical preparatioins and occasionally of equipment.
  - Drawings by Armin Hemberger for Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery & Related Pathology (1960) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Original drawing for an undetermined publication, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photograph for Lindskog and H. H. Bradshaw, "Collateral respiration: the chemical composition and volume of collaterally respired gases", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Published in American Journal of Physiology, 108 (1934): 581-582
  - Photographs for Lindskog, "The treatment of bronchiectasis by pulmonary lobectomy: summary of ten consecutive cases", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Published in Journal of the Connecticut State Medical Society, 2 (July 1938): 320-324 plus two unpaginated leaves of photographs.
  - Chart for Lindskog, "The diagnosis of bronchiogenetic carcinoma", 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Published in Journal of the Connnecticut State Medical Society, 3 (Nov. 1939): 611-612.
  - Photograph for Lindskog, "Pulmonary resection in the presence of localized empyema", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Published in Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 15 (Jan. 1943): 495-506 plus 2 pages of illustrations.
  - Photographs for Lindskog, "The surgical treatment of chronic pulmonary abscess", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Presented at the meeting of the Society of University Surgeons, Nashville, Tenn., February 10-14, 1944, and published in Surgery, 15 (May 1944): 783-788. Includes typescript, two photographs, and two negatives.
  - Photographs for Lindskog and Waltman Waters, "Surgical aspects of amoebic dysentery", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Published in Journal of the American Medical Association, 131 (May 11, 1946): 92-95.
  - Illustrations and manuscript of Lindskog, A. A. Liebow, and M. R. Hales, "Bilobectomy - surgical and anatomical considerations...", 1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Published in Journal of Thoracic Surgery, 18 (1949): 616-629. Folder also includes manuscript and some correspondence. List of patients on whom the article was based was moved to Series 6, Box 3.
  - Photograph and tables for Lindskog and R. D. Alley, "Bilateral bronchiectasis; an analysis of forty-three consecutive cases", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Published in Archives of Surgery, 6 (1950): 465-472. Includes manuscript.
  - Photographs and drawing for Lindskog, A. A. Liebow, H. Kausel, and A. Janzen, "Pulmonary ateriovenous aneurysm", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Published in Annals of Surgery, 132 (1950): 591-610. Includes manuscript.
  - Photographs for Averill Liebow, William Hales, Gustaf Liebow, and William Bloomer, "Plastic demonstrations of pulmonary pathology", n.d. (after 1946) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Photographs show experimental equipment. With mimeograph manuscript. Unpublished?
- Miscellany, Series IV
  - Typescript for C. M. Van Allen and G.E. Lindskog, "Obstructive pulmonary atelectasis" and unpublished (?) paper, C.M. Allen, "Obstructive pulmonary emphysema", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Allen was working at Peking Union Medical College. Their joint paper was published in Archives of Surgery, 21 (1930): 1195-1213.
  - Agreement with Appleton-Century-Crofts for publication of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, 3rd ed., 1970 July 10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Certificate from the American Medical Association recognizing Lindskog's service from 1946 to 1959 on the Editorial Board of Archives of Surgery (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Our Hosts, Society of Clinical Surgery," 118th meeting-Durham, N.C. - November 15 & 16, 1968" (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Two glossy sheets with photographs of surgeons, wives, and possibly women in other roles.
  - Annotated reprints by others, 1935-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Six reprints by Alfred Blalock, George S. Stevenson, Willard B. Soper, Sherwin B. Nuland, Edward A. Boyden, and William W. L. Glenn. William W. L. Glenn, "Some Reflections on the coronary bypass operation," Circulation, 14 (1972): 869-877, contains a letter from Glenn to Lindskog.
- Reprints of Lindskog's papers, 1930-1982; Series V
  Partial numbering is by Lindskog. Collection is incomplete.
  - Reprints, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reprints, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reprints, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reprints, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reprints, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reprints, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reprints, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reprints, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Reprints, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reprints, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Reprints, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    The item numbered "70" by Lindskog is an undated typescript, rather than a reprint, of "Bronchiecstasis: an analysis of 215 cases," by Lindskog and David S. Hubbell." Both "69" and "71" date from 1954.
  - Reprints, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Reprints, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Reprints, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Reprints, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reprints, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Several of these papers are historical.
  - Reprints, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    On history of surgery.
  - Reprints, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Book Reviews, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Book Reviews, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Notes on operations performed (Restricted), 1929-1974; Series VI
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is restricted because the material contains patient names. Titles have been transcribed from Dr. Lindskog's original folders
  - Selected Operative Notes, Lakeside Hospital, Cleveland, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Description of the operation procedure dictated by Lindskog, and retrospectively annotated by Dr. Lindskog in 1995. One sheet per case.
  - Selective Operative Notes, Orthopedic Surgery, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    These and the succeeding notes taken at Yale are onionskin copies of typed reports which include the name of the patient, the date, the room where the operation took place, the names of the operator and assistant operator(s), the diagnosis, the name of the operation, the type of anesthesia, a lengthy description of the surgical procedure, and a prognosis.
  - Selected Operative Notes, Urology, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Selected Operative Notes, General Surgery, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Selective Operative Notes, General Surgery, A-L, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Selective Operative Notes, General Surgery, L-Z, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1935 January (Box 3, Folder 7)
    There was no folder for 1935 January-June, but just a single item. There was a folder for July-December.
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1935 July-December (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Selective Operative Notes, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1942 January 1 -1942 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1942 July 1 - 1942 December 30 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1943 January 1-1943 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Selected Operative Notes, 1943 July 1-1943 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Selective Operative Notes, 1944 January-1944 April (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Selective Medical Notes, U.S. Naval Hospital, Philadelphia, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    These were handwritten on U.S. Naval Hospital "Clinical Record" forms. Many pages contain summaries listing names and operations.
  - Selected Operative Notes & Reports, Alphabetic, A to E, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    This series of notes, alphabetic by patient name, describes operations from 1960 to 1971. Notes are on carbon copies of forms from Grace-New Haven Community Hospital and Yale-New Haven Hospital. There are some interleaved copies of correspondence, usually to referring physicians, that date back to at least 1948.
  - Selected Operative Notes & Reports, Alphabetic, F to K, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Selected Operative Notes & Reports, Alphabetic, L to R, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Selected Operative Notes & Reports, Alphabetic, S to W, 1960-1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Lists of patients undergoing thoracic surgery, 1953-1965 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Also list of patients with mediastinal tumors, 1948-1954.
  - List of patients undergoing bilobectomy, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Removed from Series 3, Box 1, folder 22.
  - Folders on individual patients, 1949-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1-23)
    These 23 folders, arranged alphabetically by name of patient, contain correspondence with patients, family, and other other physicians. Many cases are referrals and include a letter from the referring physician.
- Lindskog's History of Surgery Annual Lectures, 1957-1987; Series VII
  These are texts of Gustaf Lindskog's annual or nearly-annual History of Surgery lectures. The Department of Surgery, sometimes joined by the Department of History of Science and Medicine, for many years sponsored a series of five history of surgery lectures held weekly in February and March. Usually they took place in the Beaumont Room or the Historical Library. The last in the series was the invited Samuel Clark Harvey Lecture named after a previous chairman of the Department of Surgery who retired in 1948. Most of these folders were found later and added to the Lindskog Papers as another series. Titles were transcribed from previous folders kept by Lindskog. Several of the lectures were published. See Lindskog's reprints in Box 2. See also other Lindskog presentations in Box 1.
  - "The History of Pulmonary Resection," Samuel Clark Harvey Lecture, 1957 February 4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Diagnostic Procedures," History of Surgery Course (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Boerhaave at Leyden: The Renaissance of Clinical Teaching," presented in the Historical Library, 1959 February 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "History of Pulmonary Abcess and its Treatments in the 19th Century," History of Surgery Lecture, [1961] (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Halsted and Modern American Surgery," History of Surgery Lecture, 1962 January 22 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Diaphragm and Diaphragmatic Hernia," History of Surgery Lecture, 1965 February 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Surgery of the Sternum and Mediastinum," History of Surgery Lecture, 1966 February 21 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Carolus Linnaeus," History of Surgery Lecture, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "American Physician-Botanists of the 19th Century", 1968 February 5 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "The Life and Times of Guillaume Dupuytren," History of Surgery Lecture, 1969 February 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Folder contains a later version of the lecture intended for publication, titled "Guillaume Dupytren: A Bicentennial Memoire," and correspondence with Arthur Baue, Chairman, Department of Surgery, and Martin C. Carey, Harvard Medical School, 1977.
  - "Ferdinand Sauerbruch and His Contributions to Thoracic Surgery," History of Surgery Lecture, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Remembrances of Former Things--Foreign Bodies," History of Surgery Lecture, 1972 January 31 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Includes a program listing a series of five lectures sponsored by by the Department of Surgery and the Department of the History of Science and Medicine. Lindskog's was the first lecture to be presented on Janaury 31, 1972. On successive weeks, lectures were to be presented by Urich H. Weill, M.D., Sherwin B. Nuland, M.D., H.C. Stansel, Jr., M.D., and finally the Samuel Clark Harvey Lecture to be given by George Rosen, M.D.
  - "The Story of Tracheoesophageal Fistula," History of Surgery Lecture, 1973 February 5 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    This lecture is in part autobiographical.
  - "Oliver Wendell Holmes," History of Surgery Lecture, 1974 February 4 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Includes slides, program for the series of history of surgery lectures in 1974, and published version of the lecture.
  - "History of Diaphragmatic Hernia," exhibit by Lindskog in the Cushing Rotunda of Yale Medical Library, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Includes typescript of a paper, "Diaphragmatic Hernia -- Historical Aspects" (unpublished?).
  - "Albrecht von Haller (1708-1777)," History of Surgery Lecture, 1977 February 14 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - "René Laennec: His Struggle Against Tuberculosis," History of Surgery Lecture, 1978 February 20 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Includes list of History of Surgery lectures for 1978.
  - "Recollections of a Surgical Training," History of Surgery Lecture, 1980 February 18 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Plus list of History of Surgery lectures, 1980. In this autobiographical lecture, Lindskog recalls incidents from his training at Harvard Medical School, including his interaction with Harvey Cushing, and from his internship at Lakeside Hospital in Cleveland.
  - "P.-C.-A. Louis (1787-1872) and the Rise of Medical Science in France," History of Surgery Lecture, 1981 March 2 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Plus list of History of Surgery lectures, 1981.
  - "The Cosmopolitan Count Rumford: Scientist, Entrepreneur and Statesman," History of Surgery Lecture, 1982 February 22 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "The Three Doctors Bigelow of Boston and Harvard," History of Surgery Lecture, 1982 March 1 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    With list of History of Surgery Lectures for 1982.
  - "Paracelsus, Renaissance Physician and Robert Browning, Visionary Poet," History of Surgery Lecture, 1984 February 6 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Plus list of "Lectures in the History of Surgery," 1984.
  - "Theodore Kocher, Pathfinder in Modern Surgery," History of Surgery Lecture, 1987 February 23 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Plus list of "Lectures in the History of Surgery," 1987.